<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ELEMENT xi:include (xi:fallback?) >
<!ATTLIST xi:include
    xmlns:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href       CDATA      #REQUIRED
    parse      (xml|text) "xml"
    encoding   CDATA      #IMPLIED >
<!ELEMENT xi:fallback ANY>
<!ATTLIST xi:fallback
    xmlsn:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
<!ENTITY % local.chapter.class "| xi:include">
]>

<!-- FILE   : UserGuide.xml
     SUBJECT: Master document for the MailFlux User Guide.
     AUTHOR : (C) Copyright 2014 by Peter C. Chapin

This is the documentation is for MailFlux users. -->
<book status="draft">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>MailFlux User's Guide</title>
    <subtitle>An SMTP Server for Experts</subtitle>
    <author>
      <firstname>Peter</firstname>
      <surname>Chapin</surname>
      <othername role="mi">C.</othername>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Vermont Technical College</orgname>
        <orgdiv>Computer Information Systems Department</orgdiv>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
    <copyright>
      <year>2016</year>
      <holder>Peter C. Chapin</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para> Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
        terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published
        by the Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES,
        with the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST. A copy
        of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <!-- Do I really want to include this revision history? -->
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.0</revnumber>
        <date>2016-01-01</date>
        <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
        <revremark>Initial release (well, not really).</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>
  <preface id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Most mail servers in use on the Internet today lack any kind of interactive user
      interface. They receive mail, forward mail, and deliver mail without directly displaying
      any information as they do so. Although mail servers typically write log files recording
      the actions they take, using these files to debug problems or to monitor the SMTP
      transactions as they occur is difficult.</para>

    <para>MailFlux is a specialized mail server that addresses these limitations. It provides an
      interactive console that the administrator can use to observe the behavior of the server
      in real time as well as to dynamically reconfigure the server. MailFlux is primarily an
      educational server, however it could also be used as a personal SMTP server or for
      debugging SMTP problems. In that respect MailFlux has the potential for real application
      outside the classroom.</para>

    <para>This document describes how to use MailFlux, with special emphasis on the program's
      unique features. The internal design of MailFlux is described in an accompanying
      Developer's Guide. If you are a mail administrator interested in using MailFlux to debug
      SMTP problems, or if you are a student interested in learning about the SMTP protocol,
      then you should read just this User's Guide. If you are a developer interested extending
      or enhancing MailFlux, then you should read both the User's Guide and the Developer's
      Guide. All MailFlux users may be especially interested in reviewing the Future Directions
      section of this guide to get an idea of what to expect in later versions of the
      program.</para>

    <para>MailFlux is covered by the GNU Public License. This basically means that you are free
      to use it in any way that you wish as well as modify it as you desire. See the file
        <filename>GPL.txt</filename> for more details. In addition, this document is also free
      (as in speech) and may be distributed and modified under the terms of the GNU Free
      Documentation License. See the file<filename>GFDL.txt</filename> for more details.</para>

    <para>If you are interested in MailFlux you might also be interested in MailStop, an mail
      client with similar design goals. MailStop is a mail user agent for experts.</para>

  </preface>

  <xi:include href="Overview.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="Standards.xml"/>

  <!-- <bibliography> ... </bibliography> -->

</book>
