<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ELEMENT xi:include (xi:fallback?) >
<!ATTLIST xi:include
    xmlns:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href       CDATA      #REQUIRED
    parse      (xml|text) "xml"
    encoding   CDATA      #IMPLIED >
<!ELEMENT xi:fallback ANY>
<!ATTLIST xi:fallback
    xmlsn:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
<!ENTITY % local.chapter.class "| xi:include">
]>

<!-- FILE   : UserGuide.xml
     SUBJECT: Master document for the MailStop User Guide.
     AUTHOR : (C) Copyright 2017 by Peter C. Chapin

This is the documentation is for MailStop users. -->
<book status="draft">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>MailStop</title>
    <subtitle>A Mail Client for Experts</subtitle>
    <author>
      <firstname>Peter</firstname>
      <surname>Chapin</surname>
      <othername role="mi">C.</othername>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Vermont Technical College</orgname>
        <orgdiv>Computer Information Systems Department</orgdiv>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
    <copyright>
      <year>2017</year>
      <holder>Peter C. Chapin</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para> Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
        terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published
        by the Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES,
        with the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST. A copy
        of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <!-- Do I really want to include this revision history? -->
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.0</revnumber>
        <date>2020-01-01</date>
        <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
        <revremark>Initial release (well, not really).</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>
  <preface id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>MailStop is an email client. Unlike most email clients that try to hide the underlying
      structure of messages from their users, MailStop tries to expose that structure. What
      makes MailStop different from other clients is that it assumes its users are (or are
      interested in becoming) email experts. It thus allows the technical details of messages to
      be viewed, navigated, and edited. MailStop allows you to explicit specify (and convert
      between) various encoding methods, manipulate the nested subparts of complex multipart
      messages, and edit extension headers on messages, to name a few features. MailStop also
      allows you direct access to the low level email protocols it uses: SMTP, POP3, and IMAP.
      In addition to supporting the features of a day to day email application, MailStop can be
      used by mail administrators to help debug mail problems and by educators as an
      instructional tool.</para>

    <para>MailStop is covered by the GNU Public License. This basically means that you are free
      to use it in any way that you wish as well as modify it as you desire. See the file
        <filename>GPL.txt</filename> for more details. In addition, this document is also free
      (as in speech) and may be distributed and modified under the terms of the GNU Free
      Documentation License. See the file<filename>GFDL.txt</filename> for more details.</para>

    <para>If you are interested in MailStop you might also be interested in MailFlux, an SMTP
      server with similar design goals. MailFlux is a mail server for experts.</para>

  </preface>

  <xi:include href="Overview.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="Standards.xml"/>

  <!-- <bibliography> ... </bibliography> -->

</book>
